Guide to the Ernst Cassirer Papers - Addition
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ernst Cassirer papers: addition
1879-1992
GEN MSS 355
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.2
The Ernst Cassirer Papers - Addition consists of manuscripts, research notes, correspondence from such persons as Hermann Cohen, Dimitry Gawronsky, Ernst Hoffmann and Raymond Klibansky and personal papers documenting the life of Ernst Cassirer. Also included are letters from Cassirer to his wife, Toni, and materials gathered by Toni Cassirer following Ernst Cassirer's death in 1945.
Total Boxes: 13
Other Storage Formats: 2 broadsides
Cassirer, Ernst, 1874-1945
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by purchase and gift from Anne Appelbaum, 1994 and 1996. Two letters are the gift of John Michael Krois, 1999. Papers in Series V. are the gift of Andrew Bano, B. W. Bano, J. Bano, and Esther Harris.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. The letters to Toni Cassirer from Ernst Cassirer in boxes 4-5 are restricted until 2021 Aug 30. Restricted Fragile in box 12 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
Ernst Cassirer Papers, GEN MSS 98
ERNST CASSIRER (1874-1945)
Ernst Alfred Cassirer: philosopher, educator, writer, and prominent member of the neo-Kantian movement. For a more complete description, see the Ernst Cassirer Papers (GEN MSS 98).
Scope and Contents
The Ernst Cassirer Papers - Addition includes papers which supplement those found in GEN MSS 98. For this reason, they have been organized into similar series: Essays and Lectures, Correspondence, and Personal Papers. Essays and Lectures includes a number of pieces on Goethe as well as offprints and printed versions of Cassirer essays, the holograph drafts for many of which can be found in GEN MSS 98. The Correspondence is organized into General Correspondence, which includes letters from Gertrud Bing and Fritz Saxl, Hermann Cohen, Dimitry Gawronsky, Ernst Hoffmann, Raymond Klibansky, and Aby Warburg, Third-Party Correspondence, which contains two letters between Kurt Reizler and Aby Warburg, discussing the University of Frankfurt's offer of a chair in philosophy to Cassirer, and Family Correspondence, which contains letters from Ernst Cassirer to several of his immediate family. The Family Correspondence also contains an extensive run of letters from Ernst to Toni Cassirer for the years 1902-1943. This portion of the Cassirer correspondence is Restricted until 2021. Series III, Personal Papers, consists mainly of materials documenting Cassirer's academic career, such as degrees and membership certificates. Also included are a journal, early school notebooks, and a few photographs.
The Addition also includes a small group of Toni Cassirer Papers which, for the most part, pertain to her husband, almost all of them dating from after Ernst Cassirer's death in 1945. The files include letters (mainly of condolence), several third-party letters, memorials, articles about Ernst Cassirer, and prints and clippings.
Series V., Papers from Grandchildren of Martin Cassirer, contains letters (principally to Martin Cassirer), copies of eulogies, clippings, and photographs.
Philosophy, German; Philosophy, Modern; Germany -- Intellectual life -- 20th Century; Authors, German; Philosophers; Geheeb-Cassirer, Edith, 1885-1982; Cassirer, Ernst, 1874-1945; Cassirer, Toni Bondy, 1883-; Cohen, Hermann, 1842-1918; Gawronsky, Dimitry; Hoffmann, Ernst, 1880-1952; Klibansky, Raymond, 1905-2005
- Essays and Lectures, 1919-1946; Series I; 0.40' (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Essays and Lectures (Box 1), is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - "Die Antike und Die Entstehung der Exakten Wissenschaft", offprint, [1932] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Aphasis (Raum - Zeit - Zahl)", notes, holograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Empty folder] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Empty folder] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Die Bedeutung des Sprachproblems für die Entstehung der Neueren Philosophie", offprint, [1927] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Bemerkungen zum Faustfragment und zur Faustdichtung"
    - Draft, holograph, 1942 Apr 14 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Typescript, 1942 Apr 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Typescript, carbon, 1942 Apr 14 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Deutschland und Westeuropa im Spiegel der Geistesgeschichte", printed version, InterNationes, 1931 Oct 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "'Geist' und 'Leben' in der Philosophie der Gegenwart", offprint, [1928] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Goethe Vorlesung"
    - Erste Vorlesung, holograph, corrected, 1941 Mar (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Zweite Vorlesung, holograph, corrected, with notes, [1941 Mar] (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letzte Vorlesung, holograph, corrected, 1941 Mar 12 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Vierte Vorlesung: Lily Schönemann, holograph, corrected, [1941 Mar] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Fünfte Vorlesung, Sechste Vorlesung: Rückblick und Ausblick, Der 'Urfaust', holograph, [1941 Mar] (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Drittes Kapitel: Strassburg und Sesenheim, holograph, corrected, with notes, 1940-41 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Goethes Idee der Bildung und Erziehung", offprint, Pädagogisches Zentralblatt, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Die Idee der Religion bei Lessing und Mendelssohn", printed version, Festgabe zum Zehnjährigen Bestehen der Akadamie für Wissenschaft des Judentums, 1919-29 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Judaism and the Modern Political Myths" printed version, Contemporary Jewish Record, 1944 Apr (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Judendomen och de Moderna Politiska Myterna", printed version, Judisk Tidskrift, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Der junge Goethe", typescript, corrected, 1940 Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Kant's Stellung in der deutschen Geistesgeschichte", printed version, Jahresbericht für die Hamburgische Universitätsgesellschaft, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letter of recommendation for on Albert G[örland?], typescript, corrected (Box 1, Folder 22a)
  - Letter of recommendation for Ernst Hoffmann, notes, holograph (Box 1, Folder 22b)
  - "The Myth of the State", printed version, Fortune Magazine, [1944]
  - "Philosophie der Aufklärung", notes, holograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Das Problem des Schönen und der Kunst in Platons Dialogen", offprint, Vorträge der Bibliothek Warburg, 1922-23 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Pythagoras and the Pythagoreans", typescript, corrected, [1942] (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Structuralism in Modern Linguistics", printed version, Word: Journal of the Linguistic Circle of New York, 1945 Aug (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Notes for various works, holograph and typescript (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Correspondence, 1892-1945; Series II; 1.40' (4 boxes)
  Series II, Correspondence is divided into three subseries: General Correspondence contains letters to Cassirer, unless otherwise specified; Third-party Correspondence contains letters between others. Family Correspondence contains letters by Cassirer, unless otherwise specified. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically.
  - GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE
    - Bahr, Hermann, 1917 Nov 18 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Bedford College for Women (University of London), 1934-35 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Bing, Gertrud; Saxl, Fritz, 1921-37, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
    - Camp Concordia (Concordia, Kan.), 1945 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      [Prisoner of War Camp]
    - Cohen, Hermann, 1901-29 (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
    - Cohen, Martha
    - Dekan, Herr, 1926 Feb 12 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      [Draft of letter by Cassirer to the Dean of the Philosophisches Seminar, Universität Hamburg - possibly A. Kïrchler]
    - Deutsche Botschaft, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - English Goethe Society, 1935 Mar 11 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Eugene Field Society, 1944 Dec 20 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Frank, Philipp, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Gawronsky, Dimitry; Gawronsky, Maria, 1911-25 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Görland, Albert, 1938 Nov 26 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      [Draft of letter by Cassirer]
    - Gundolf, Elisabeth, 1931 Aug 7 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Hägerström, Axel, 1937 Mar 3 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Hamburg, Germany. Verfassungsfeier Festrede, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      [includes draft of letter by Cassirer]
    - Hartmann, Nicolai, 1908-30 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Hashagen, J., 1934 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Hedvall, J. Arvid, 1937 Feb 26 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Hendel, Charles [Yale University. Dept. of Philosophy], 1941 Jan 10 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Hensel, Elisabeth, 1931 Feb 26 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Hensel, Paul, 1906-29 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Hönigswald, Richard, 1937 Apr 8 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Hoffmann, Ernst, 1916-38, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 52-59)
      [Letters also signed by "Thea" and "Elsa"]
    - Jacobsson, Malte, 1933-35, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Klibansky, Raymond, 1932-38, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Kramers, Hendrik Anthony, 1937 Mar 26 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Laue, Max, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Litt, Theodor, 1924-37 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Misès, Professor, De, 1937 Mar 3 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Münsterberg, Hugo, 1913 Mar 13 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Passarge, Siegfried, 1921 Apr 22 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Reichenbach, Hans, 1937 Mar 10 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Siemsen, Hans, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Singer, Kurt, 1945 Mar 10 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Stern, William, 1919 Jul 30 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Upsala Universitets, 1933-34 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Vossler, Karl, 1927-32 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Warburg, Aby, 1916-29 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Wind, Edgar, 1937 Apr 6 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Yura, T., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 76)
      With: offprint of Japanese translation of "Formen und Formwandlungen des philosophischen Wahrheitsbegriffs" (Rektoratsrede).
    - Unidentified correspondents, incoming, 1933-39 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Unidentified correspondents, outgoing, 1930-39 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - THIRD-PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Reizler, Kurt to Aby Warburg, 1928 Jul 16 (Box 3, Folder 78a)
    - Warburg, Aby to Kurt Reizler, 1928 Jul 19 (Box 3, Folder 78b)
  - FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Cassirer, Bruno, 1893 Jul 10 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Cassirer, Clara, 1893 Nov 5 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Cassirer, Edith Geheeb, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Cassirer, Eduard; Cassirer, Eugenie, 1892-1928 (Box 3, Folder 82-85)
    - Cassirer, Grete, 1899 Jun 16 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Cassirer, Hedwig, 1893, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Cassirer, Heinz, [1922 Jun 4] (Box 3, Folder 88)
      [from Heinz to Toni Cassirer]
    - Cassirer, Paul, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Cassirer, Toni, 1902-1905 (Box 4, Folder 90-104)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted until 2021. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
    - Cassirer, Toni, 1906-1943, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 105-134)
    - Geheeb-Cassirer, Edith
      Related Materials
      See: Cassirer, Edith Geheeb, Box 3, folder 81
- Personal Papers, 1879-1945; Series III; 0.40' (1 box)
  Series III, Personal Papers is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Announcement for Theodor Lindner's book, Der Krieg gegen Frankreich, 1895 (Box 6, Folder 135)
    With: autograph notes by Cassirer.
  - Clippings, 1924-36 (Box 6, Folder 136)
  - Circular letter requesting biographies from faculty members at Universität Hamburg, 1926 Feb 12 (Box 6, Folder 137)
  - Course completion certificates
    - Friedrich Wilhelms Universität zu Berlin, 1892-95 (Box 6, Folder 138)
    - Johannes-Gymnasium zu Breslau, 1892 Mar 10 (Box 6, Folder 139)
    - Philipps Universität Marburg., 1896-99 (Box 6, Folder 140)
    - Ruprecht-Karls-Universität Heidelberg, 1893 Aug (Box 6, Folder 141)
    - Universität Leipzig, 1893 Feb 27 (Box 6, Folder 142)
    - Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München, 1896 Oct 3 (Box 6, Folder 143)
  - Curriculum vitae, [1921, 1945] (Box 6, Folder 144-145)
  - Doctoral certificates, University of Marburg, 1900, 1906 (Box 6, Folder 146)
  - Family tree, n.d.
  - Honorary doctorate, Göteborgs universitet, 1941
  - Honorary memberships
    - Kant-Gesellschaft, 1931 Jun
    - Kungl. Vitterhets, historie och antikvitets akademien, 1940 Feb 6
    - Kungliga Vetenskaps-och Vitterhets- Samhället, Göteborg, 1935 Dec 9
  - Invitations, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 147)
  - Invitation to wedding between Otto Bondy and Julie Cassirer, 1879 (Box 6, Folder 148)
  - Journal of Swedish lessons, [ca. 1935] (Box 6, Folder 149)
  - Patent certifying Cassirer as Professor, 1914 Feb 17 (Box 6, Folder 150)
  - Photographs
    - Ernst Cassirer, ca. 1930-45 (Box 6, Folder 151)
    - Unidentified, 1960, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 152)
  - Prize list for Universität Marburg, 1898-99 (Box 6, Folder 153)
    Contains list of student's awards as determined by various departments
  - Student Notebooks
    - Friedrich-Wilhelms-Universität Berlin, 1893-94 (Box 6, Folder 154)
    - Philipps-Universität Marburg, 1896-99 (Box 6, Folder 155)
    - Universität Leipzig, 1892-93 (Box 6, Folder 156)
  - "Über Ernst Cassirer" by Hermann Bahr, offprint, signed, [1917 Nov] (Box 6, Folder 157)
  - University of Glasgow graduation, printed materials, 1936 Jun (Box 6, Folder 158)
- Toni Cassirer Papers, 1929-1992; Series IV; 0.60' (1 box)
  Materials in Series IV are arranged by type and alphabetically.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - General Correspondence
      - Bing, Gertrud, 1948 Aug 27 (Box 7, Folder 159)
      - Cassirer, Vera, 1945 May 8 (Box 7, Folder 160)
      - Engel, Sophia, 1945 Apr 15 (Box 7, Folder 161)
      - Einstein, Martha, 1945 Apr 16 (Box 7, Folder 162)
      - Hoffmann, Ernst and Thea, 1946 Jun 26 (Box 7, Folder 163)
      - Kroehling, Herta, 1953 Apr 17 (Box 7, Folder 164)
      - Litt, Theodor, 1953 Apr 25 (Box 7, Folder 165)
      - Margenau, Henry, 1945 Apr 19 (Box 7, Folder 166)
      - Pasternak, Boris, photostat, 1959 Aug 19
      - Letters of condolence, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 167-170)
        Includes: Letters from Charles Hendel, Richard Hönigswald, Hans Reichenbach, Max Rudolf, Jean Wahl, and Edgar Wind
      - Telegrams of condolence, 1945 Apr (Box 7, Folder 171)
      - Letter fragments, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 172)
        Includes letter from Dimitry Gawronsky
    - Third-party correspondence
      - Eugene Davidson to Charles Hendel, 1945 May 11 (Box 7, Folder 173)
        [Forwarding letter from Karl C. Teufel]
      - Martha Heinrich to Lisbeth Cassirer, 1960 May 2 (Box 7, Folder 174)
      - Dr. Frieda Fromm-Reichmann to Anne Appelbaum, 1955 Mar 31 (Box 7, Folder 175)
      - Raymond Klibansky to Anne Appelbaum (Box 7, Folder 176)
      - John Michael Krois to Anne Appelbaum, 1992 Jul 28 (Box 7, Folder 177)
        Also contains: Typescript of Krois's work as editor of Nachgelassene Manuskripte und Texte.
  - PAPERS CONCERNING ERNST CASSIRER
    - Memorial Addresses
      - Address by James Gutmann, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 178)
      - Address by Hajo Holborn, typescript and carbon, 1945 Jun 1 (Box 8, Folder 179)
      - Address by Walter Solmitz, typescript, 1945 Apr 16 (Box 8, Folder 180)
      - Conference of Methods in Philosophy and the Sciences, address by Kurt Riezler, typescript carbon, 1945 May 6 (Box 8, Folder 181)
      - Columbia University, Department of Philosophy, typescript carbon, 1945 Apr (Box 8, Folder 182)
      - "Erinnerungen an Ernst Cassirer" by Frederick Walter Lenz, offprint, Monatshefte, [1945] (Box 8, Folder 183)
      - Philosophy Club of New York, address by Charles Hendel, typescript and offprint, Philosophy and Phenomenological Research, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 184-185)
    - Writings
      - Articles about Cassirer, clippings, 1945-53 (Box 8, Folder 186)
      - "Bibliographie des Textes sur Ernst Cassirer" by Robert Nadeau, offprint, Revue internationale de philosophie, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 187)
      - Book reviews, clippings, 1945-50, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 188)
      - Columbia University, Annual Commemoration Service, 1946 Jan 20 (Box 8, Folder 189)
      - "Ernst Cassirer" by Arne Worren, printed version, Vinduet: Gyldendals Tidsskrift for Litteratur, 1950 Oct (Box 8, Folder 190)
      - "Ernst Cassirer in England" by Toni Cassirer, offprint, Sguardi su la Filosofia Contemporanea, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 191)
      - "Ernst Cassirer und die Deutsche Philologie" by Heinz Bluhm, offprint, Monatshefte, 1945 Nov (Box 8, Folder 192)
      - "Ernst Cassirer und Die Moderne Wissenschaftslage" by David Baumgardt, offprint, Zeitschrift für Religions- und Geistesgeschichte, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 193)
      - Obituaries, clippings, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 194)
      - "The Problem of Knowledge" book review by David Baumgardt, printed version, The Hibbert Journal, 1950 Oct (Box 8, Folder 195)
      - "Rede auf Ernst Cassirer", printed program, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 196)
        Contains reprint of opening words by Eduard Bötticher and address by Wilhelm Flitner
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Clippings on various subjects, 1929-50 (Box 8, Folder 197)
    - Offprints on philosophy subjects, 1958-60 (Box 8, Folder 198)
    - Print: Engraving, "Le Bosquet de Bacchus", n.d.
    - Print: View of Oxford, n.d.
    - Print: View of Oxford, n.d.
    - Unidentified typescript pages, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 199)
    - Wrappers, n.d.
      Original wrappers in which papers were received, many containing identifying annotations.
- Papers from Grandchildren of Martin Cassirer, 1900-1950; Series V; 0.20' (1 box)
  Materials in Series V are arranged by type and alphabetically.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Cassirer, Ernst to Martin Cassirer, 1913-24 (Box 13, Folder 218)
    - Cassirer, Ernst, Jenny and [Eduard?] to Martin Cassirer, 1901 May 4 (Box 13, Folder 219)
    - Cassirer, Ernst and Toni to Martin Cassirer, 1904-44 (Box 13, Folder 220)
      [1904 postcard is photograph of Ernst and Toni Cassirer]
    - Cassirer, Jenny to Martin Cassirer, 1900 Nov 21 (Box 13, Folder 221)
    - Cassirer, Toni to Lisbeth Cassirer, 1927 Sep 4 (Box 13, Folder 222)
      [postcard with photograph of Ernst and Toni Cassirer]
    - Cassirer, Toni to Martin Cassirer, 1928 Sep 3 (Box 13, Folder 223)
      [postcard with photograph of Anne, Ernst, and Toni Cassirer]
    - "Deine Vater" to unidentified, 190? (Box 13, Folder 224)
      [fragment]
  - EULOGIES
    - Cassirer, Ernst, "Grabrede" [for Fritz Cassirer], printed version, [1926] (Box 13, Folder 225)
    - Cassirer, Ernst, "Hermann Cohen", offprint, 1918 May (Box 13, Folder 226)
    - Gawronsky, Dimitry, "Gedenkrede fur Ernst Cassirer", typescript, 1945 Apr 16 (Box 13, Folder 227)
    - Hall, Earls, "On Ernst Cassirer", typescript carbon, 1945 Ar 16 (Box 13, Folder 228)
    - Holborn, Hajo, "Ernst Cassirer", typescript carbon, 1945 (Box 13, Folder 229)
  - OTHER ITEMS
    - Clippings on Ernst Cassirer, 1929-50 (Box 13, Folder 230)
    - Photographs, 1921, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 231)
      2 prints of Ernst Cassirer; 1 print of Ernst and Toni Cassirer
- Oversize, 4.0' (3 boxes)
  - "The Myth of the State" [Fortune Magazine], printed version (in Series I), [1944] (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 200)
  - Honorary memberships
    - Kant-Gesellschaft (in Series III), 1931 Jun (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 201)
    - Kungl. Vitterhets, historie och antikvitets akademien (in Series III), 1940 Feb 6 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 202)
    - Kungliga Vetenskaps-och Vitterhets- Samhället, Göteborg (in Series III), 1935 Dec 9 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 203)
  - Photographs - Ernst Cassirer (in Series III), [1930], n.d. (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 204)
  - Family tree (in Series III), n.d. (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 205)
  - Honorary doctorate, Göteborgs universitet (in Series III), 1941 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 206)
  - Pasternak, Boris, photostat (in Series IV), 1959 Aug 19 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 207)
  - Print: Engraving, "Le Bosquet de Bacchus" (in Series IV), n.d. (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 208)
  - Print: View of Oxford (in Series IV), n.d. (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 209)
  - Doctoral certificate, University of Marburg (in Series III), 1900 (Box (Broadside), Folder 210)
  - Print: View of Oxford (in Series IV), n.d. (Box (Broadside), Folder 211)
  - Wrappers (in Series IV), n.d. (Box 11 (Oversize), Folder 212-214)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.20' (1 box)
  - Box 6, folder 136 (Box 12, Folder 215)
  - Box 8, folder 186 (Box 12, Folder 216)
  - Box 8, folder 194 (Box 12, Folder 217)